Finding Aid for Ruth M. Barnard Papers, 1975-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ruth M. Barnard papers 1975-2000
Barnard, Ruth M.
03104 Aa 2
Ruth Barnard was a professor at the University of Michigan School of Nursing from 1975 to 2000. The collection contains material related to her research, teaching and participation in a wide range of School of Nursing and university committees.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
4 linear feet
The collection was donated by Ruth Barnard (Donor No. 9229 ) in July 2002.
The collection is open without restriction.
Ruth M. Barnard was born in Minnesota in 1935. She earned her bachelor's degree in nursing in 1958 from Johns Hopkins University, her master's degree in nursing administration in 1965 from Boston University, and her Ph.D. in nursing rehabilitation and research in 1973 from New York University. She practiced nursing in a variety of settings between 1958 and 1971 and directed nursing research at Mount Sinai Hospital in New York City from 1971 to 1975.
Barnard took a position as associate professor at the University of Michigan School of Nursing in 1975 where she remained until her retirement in 2000. She began her tenure as a faculty member in the School of Nursing Research Area, and from 1982 to 1988 chaired the Medical-Surgical Nursing Area and directed the Graduate Program in Medical-Surgical Nursing. She taught both graduate and undergraduate courses and later served as Academic Information Specialist in the Office of Academic Affairs. The University of Michigan Board of Regents granted emeritus status to Barnard in 2002.
Barnard was an active member of the University of Michigan's Rho Chapter of Sigma Theta Tau, the national honor society of nursing, as well as state and local nursing organizations. Her research interests included women's health, specifically menopause, and the use of technology in professional information exchange.
Technological issues in the field of nursing held a strong interest for Barnard and led her to make significant efforts to bring the School of Nursing into the information age. She supported world wide web and computer usage, the UMTV evolution and videotaping of various school activities. She was an advocate for computer literacy in the nursing field and for computer use in the classroom, presenting workshops and demonstrations to students and practicing nurses. Some of her early research examined the effects of teleconferencing on nursing research. She served as an informal consultant on web-based and computer-related issues and, as Academic Information Specialist, provided instruction and support for faculty employing advanced technologies to teach both at the university and through distance learning and led in the development of the School of Nursing Information Center.
The papers of Ruth M. Barnard document her career at the University of Michigan School of Nursing. The collection is arranged in four series: Biographical/Personal Files; Presentations, Publications, and Research Files; Committee and Task Force Files; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Barnard, Ruth M.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan. Medical-Surgical Nursing Area.
- Biographical/Personal Files
  Biographical/Personal Files (0.3 feet) provide an overview of Barnard's career through various versions of her curriculum vitae. (More recent versions can be found in the Topical Files series under Teaching: Evaluations.) Also included in this series is correspondence with colleagues and students, which demonstrate her involvement with Sigma Theta Tau, the National Honor Society of Nursing, and School of Nursing committees as well as her commitment to the success and education of her students.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1976-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1999 (Box 1)
  - Thank Yous and Memories 1978-1998 (Box 1)
- Presentations, Publications, and Research Files
  Presentations, Publications, and Research Files (0.5 feet) document Barnard's academic activity. Her research interests included patient assessment and menopause. These research interests are reflected in grant proposals as well as presentations and publications resulting from completed projects.
  - Grant Proposals
    - Cognitive Impairment 1994-1998 (Box 1)
    - Community Home Health Care Nursing Network 1997 (Box 1)
    - Effect of Teleconferencing on Nursing Research 1979 (Box 1)
    - Health Indices in a Primary Care Setting 1977 (Box 1)
    - Integrated Assessment in Primary Care and Nursing 1977 (Box 1)
    - Psychoneuroimmunological Measures 1976 (Box 1)
    - Social Functioning as a Predictor of Health Status and Utilization 1978 (Box 1)
  - Menopause Research 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    (3 folders)
  - Presentations 1973-1992 (Box 1)
    (2 folders)
  - Publications 1974-1996 (Box 1)
- Committee and Task Force Files
  The Committee and Task Force Files series (2.1 feet) reflects Barnard's involvement in policy-making and operations of both the School of Nursing and the University of Michigan as a whole. The series has been divided into two subseries accordingly: School of Nursing, and University of Michigan. These files are representative, though not comprehensive, of her committee and task force membership and leadership. Barnard was particularly valued for her expertise in issues surrounding research, research ethics, and information technology.
  - School of Nursing
    - Appointments, Promotions and Tenure Committee
      - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Center for Nursing Research (CNR) Search Committee 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - Facility Planning Committee 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Faculty Recruitment and Search Committee 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Human Subjects Review Committee
      - 1976-1982 (Box 2)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Information Technology
      - Computing Policy and Advisory Committee 1980 (Box 2)
      - DoIT: Instructional Technology Task Force 1994-1995 (Box 2)
      - Future Computing Environment Migration Team 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
        (includes UMTV)
      - Technology Task Force 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Mission, Philosophy and Objectives Committee 1984 (Box 2)
      (subcommittee of Graduate Curriculum Committee)
    - Ph.D. Task Force on Nursing Components 1981 (Box 2)
    - Research Ethics Committee 1976-1982 (Box 2)
    - Space Planning Committee 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate Coordinating Committee 1997 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Human Subjects Research Chairs Committee
      - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Military Officer Education Program Committee 1983-1988, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Senate Advisory Committee
      - Research Policies 1979-1980 (Box 3)
      - Rules 1995-1997, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Tenure 1992-1997, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - University Hospital
      - Blue Cross Ceiling Task Force 1975 (Box 3)
      - Centralized Quality Assurance Committee
        - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
        - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (1.1 feet) cover a range of subjects, which, again, mirror Barnard's active participation in the activities of the School of Nursing. Of particular interest are files relating to information technology issues and to curriculum, which include faculty records and teaching information such as course syllabi and annual faculty evaluations.
  - Biologic Research Space 1991 (Box 3)
  - BSN State Board Study 1976 (Box 3)
  - Carl Pursell Honor 1992 (Box 3)
  - Center of Excellence: Center for Enhancement and Restoration of Cognitive Function (CERCF) 1995 (Box 3)
  - Faculty
    - Area Chairpersons Meeting Summaries 1980 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Teaching Research Courses 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Program Faculty Meeting Minutes
      - 1985 (Box 4)
      - 1996 (Box 4)
  - Information Technology
    - School of Nursing Computer Networking Proposals 1988, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - School of Nursing Information Center 1995 (Box 4)
    - School of Nursing Information Technology 1994-1998 (Box 4)
    - School of Nursing UMTV 1994, 1996 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Computer Network Proposal 1981 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan User Requirements for Instructional Technology, Report from Faculty Task Force 1993 (Box 4)
  - Medical-Surgical Area
    - Faculty workload
      - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Memos 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Minutes
      - 1976 (Box 4)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 4)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
    - New Curriculum 1985 (Box 4)
    - Publicity 1986 (Box 4)
  - Medical-Surgical Undergraduate Pilot Project 1995 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Board of Nursing 1986 (Box 4)
  - Ph.D. Program Grant Proposal 1982 (Box 4)
  - Research Area
    - Files of Course Handouts 1976 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1975-1979 (Box 4)
    - Orientation 1975 (Box 4)
  - Symposia
    - AIDS Presentation 1987 (Box 4)
    - Clinical Nurse Specialist Symposium 1979 (Box 4)
    - Contemporary Issues in Women's Health 1981 (Box 4)
  - Teaching
    - Course Syllabi 1975-2000, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Evaluations 1981-1999 (Box 4)
  - Teaching Nursing Homes 1984 (Box 4)
  - Undergraduate Evaluation by Mary Schroder 1978 (Box 4)
Related Material
For additional related records, researchers may wish to consult the following records also held at the Bentley Historical Library:
University of Michigan. School of Nursing
University of Michigan. Medical-Surgical Nursing Area
University of Michigan. Academic Women's Caucus